Guide to the Marc Kagan Research Collection on the Transit Workers Union TAM.679
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marc Kagan Research Collection on the Transit Workers Union
1980-2023
2001-2003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kagan, Marc
TAM.679
4.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 28 computer files
16.15 Gigabytes
Marc Kagan is a union activist and educator who was a member and leader of the Transport Union Workers (TWU) Local 100 from 1984 through 2010. Kagan's union involvement increased during the 1990s, and he joined the New Directions caucus challenging the leadership of the TWU. In 2000, New Directions leader Roger Toussaint was elected union president, and Kagan became his chief of staff. In 2010, Kagan left the union over a dispute concerning the 2002 contract he helped negotiate. This collection documents the general operations of the TWU during the late 1990s and early 2000s, as well as Kagan's personal membership in and relationship with the organization as both a union member and its chief of staff. The majority of materials document the negotiations surrounding the 2002 union contract including grievances and implementation issues, as well as concerns about sick leave, health benefits, safety issues, apprenticeship implementation, and child care support. The files are both paper and electronic, though the bulk of the records are paper.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Marc Kagan in 2015. The accession number associated with this gift is 2015.057. Kagan donated an accretion of electronic oral history interview recordings in January 2023; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.027.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Marc Kagan is a union activist and educator who was a member and leader of the Transport Union Workers (TWU) Local 100 from 1984 through 2010. After graduating from Yale University, Kagan took a job as a mechanic and forklift operator at the 207th Street subway yard in Upper Manhattan. Kagan's union involvement grew during the 1990s, and he joined the New Directions caucus that challenged the leadership of the TWU. In 2000, New Directions leader Roger Toussaint was elected union president, and Kagan became his chief of staff. In 2010, Kagan left the union over a dispute concerning the 2002 contract he helped negotiate and became a history teacher at the Bronx High School of Science. He is the older brother of Supreme Court Justice Elena Kagan.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the general operations of the Transport Workers Union (TWU) during the late 1990s and early 2000s, as well as Kagan's personal membership in and relationship with the organization as both a union member and its chief of staff. Materials include memoranda, correspondence, oral histories, and newspaper clippings concerning negotiations about the 2002 union contract including grievances and implementation issues, as well as concerns about sick leave, health benefits, safety issues, apprenticeship implementation, and child care support. The electronic oral histories were conducted by Kagan and feature current and former TWU members on the subject of the New Directions opposition caucus and a 2005 TWU strike. The files are both paper and electronic, though the bulk of the records are paper.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Labor unions -- Organizing -- New York (N.Y.); Transport workers -- New York (N.Y.); Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 100; Kagan, Marc
- President's Office, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Correspondence, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
- Correspondence Under My Signature, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Contract Grievances Decisions, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- TWA/ TA Meeting Notes And Information, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Car Division Issues, undated (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- 12/1/01 Meeting, 2001 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence Between Local 100 and TWU International, undated (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
- Kagan Memos, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Naomi Allen/Marc Kagan Charges, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- TWU Local 100 Express Newspaper, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
- Car Equipment: Seniority and Broadbanding, undated (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Transit Railcar Technology Specialist: New Title, Preliminary Negotiations, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- June 2001 Executive Board Package (Box 2, Folder 10)
- New York City Transit Rules and Regulations, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Various Stipulation, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Kagan-Toussaint Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous Two, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Proposal Sorto Stewards Training, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Health Benefit Crisis, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
- Track Work, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Transition Issues for TWU Local 100, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- 1999 Contract (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Marxist-Leninist Party Transit Flyers and Analysis, 1980-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Final Days Main Table Bargaining (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Dec 2002 Main Table Bargaining, December 2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Nov 2002 Main Table Bargaining, November 2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Aug 2002 Bargaining Notes: General, August 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Sept 2002 Bargaining Notes: General, September 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 2002 TWU Contract (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Bargaining Information from Various Departments and Divisions, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Sick Leave Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Medical Appeal and Workers Comp Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Health Benefits Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
- Safety Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Accident Review System, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Discipline Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- New Technology and Farming Out Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Child Care, Discrimination, Harassment, Employee Rights, and FMLA Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Apprenticeship Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Bus Commingling Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- TA/OA Surface Operators Bargaining, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Expanded Joint Executive Board, 2002 June 29 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- May 2002 Bargaining Preparations (Box 4, Folder 4)
- 2002 TA Budget (Box 4, Folder 5)
- FOIAs and Other Information Requests and Some Responses, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- 2002 Health Benefit Implementation, Including Arbitration (Box 4, Folder 7)
- 2002 Contract Implementation Issues (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
- Cornell Negotiations Training, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Disciplinary Statistics, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- June 2002 Bargaining Preparations (Box 4, Folder 12)
- July 2002 Bargaining Papers (Box 4, Folder 13)
- 2002 Member Organizing Efforts (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
- 2002 Contract Vote (Box 4, Folder 16)
- 2002 Contract Injunction Against Officer of TWU Local 100 (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
- Newspaper Reportage, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
- Other Bargaining: 1119 SEU ATU 1056, circa 2002 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- TWU Local 100 Calendar, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Off Table Memos and Flyers, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Contract Radification Binder, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
- Marc Kagan/ TWU Local 100 Oral History Interviews, circa 2005; cuid36927; 761 Megabytes on 28 computer files (Box 5, Folder 5, Box Electronic Records, Item TW_TAM_679_ER_1)
  Scope and Contents
  Interview subjects include: Alan Saly, Arthur Schwartz, Dave Katzman, Eddie Kay, George McAnanama, Irving Lee, JP Patafio, Ken Margolies, Marty Goodman, Mike Jerome, Sean Ahern, Terry Meginniss, and Tim Schermerhorn.
- Marc Kagan/TWU Local 100 Oral History Interviews, 2015-2022; cuid36941; 8.15 Gigabytes on 65 computer files (Box Electronic Records, Item TW_TAM_679_ER_2)
  Interview subjects include: Stanley Aronwitz, Joe Campbell, Ken Carl, Anita Clinton, Vic Constantino, Bruce Dickstein, Steve Downs, Tony Feliciano, Chris Fox, Joel Fredericson, Jim Gannon, Joe Gayol, Robin Gillespie, Arthur Goldberg, Bill Gottlieb, Sonny (Harold) Hall, Larry Hanley, Kevin Harrington, Joe James, Dave Katzman, George MacAnanama, John McCarthy, Terry Meginniss, Gene Monette, John Mooney, JP Patafio, Louis Russo Jr., Roy Schulman, Robert Schwab, Arthur SChwartz, Michael Scott, Jesse Sharkey, John Simino, Eileen Sullivan, Marian Swerdlow, Tim Schermerhorn, Mike Tutrone, Jarvis Tyner, Nick Unger, and Progressive Action.